Finding Aid for the Pat And Lily Okura Papers LSC.2367
UCLA Library Special Collections
Pat and Lily Okura papers
1912-2009
UCLA Library Special Collections
Okura, Pat, 1911-
Okura, Lily, 1919-
LSC.2367
90.2 linear feet (184 boxes, 29 flat boxes, 15 shoeboxes, and 1 oversize box)
The lives of Pat and Lily Okura represent Japanese American civil rights leadership in the face of adversity and discrimination. Their life histories give testament to service and dedication for social justice, especially for Asian American and Pacific Islander (AAPI) communities. Their papers range from 1912-2009 and contain files that document K. Patrick Okura's professional career, minority health advocacy, appointments, consultancies, community engagement, Lily A. Okura's life, involvement with the Japanese American Citizens League (JACL), World War II experience, personal records, correspondence, and resources. Source: "K. Patrick and Lily A. Okura Collection: Registry." UCLA Asian American Studies Center. http://www.aasc.ucla.edu/okura/okura_registry.aspx.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL/AUDIO/AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Digital/audio/audiovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Glen I. Komatsu, 2005.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9990062293606533
Custodial History
This collection was acquired by Library Special Collections Manuscripts Curator Genie Guerard and Asian American Studies Librarian Marjorie Lee. The collection was transferred to Library Special Collections from the Asian American Studies Center for final rehousing and description in August and September 2019.
Biographical / Historical
K. Patrick Okura (1911-2005) was born in Los Angeles, California, the eldest son of Japanese immigrants. He attended University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA), obtained a Bachelor's degree in Psychology (1933), and became the first Asian American to graduate with a Master's degree in Psychology (1935) at UCLA. He was also the first Japanese American to play on their varsity baseball team. Later he received an honorary Doctorate from the Phillips Graduate Institute (2001). After UCLA, Okura worked in various positions for the City of Los Angeles. From 1939-1942, he worked as Personnel Technician to the Los Angeles City Civil Service, serving as the highest-ranking Japanese American in the city and the first Japanese American to be hired by the city for an administrative position.
After Pearl Harbor was attacked, however, the Los Angeles Times and Examiner labeled Okura as "the most dangerous Japanese American" and he faced accusations of plotting to sabotage the city's water and power supply. He was pushed to resign but refused, and was eventually fired. World War II continued to impact Okura when he and his family, along with thousands of other Americans of Japanese descent, were forcibly removed to the Santa Anita Assembly Center and subsequently transferred to various detention camps.
Lily and her family were also forcibly removed to Santa Anita, and upon closure of the center, Lily and Pat were married in October, 1941. Offered a staff psychologist position by Father Flanagan of Boys Town, a boys' home in Omaha, Nebraska, the Okuras decided to relocate to the Midwest and re-establish themselves for the next 30 years. Not only did he become well established in his professional career and in the community, Okura also took an active role as a civil rights leader. A member of Japanese American Citizens League (JACL) since the 1930s, he served as National President from 1962-1964. Under his leadership, JACL participated in the first March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom in 1963, and was actively involved with reparations from the U.S. government for the World War II incarceration of Japanese Americans. In 1978, the organization bestowed their highest honor on Okura when he was named Japanese American of the Biennium for his contributions to the JACL.
Okura is a recognized pioneer in Asian Pacific American, minority, and community mental health communities. Beginning in 1971, Okura became the Executive Assistant to Dr. Bertram S. Brown, the Director of the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH). Okura was in a strategic position for more than two decades advocating for and endorsing financial support for the health and welfare needs of Asian American/Pacifc Islander (AAPI) communities. In 1980, the UCLA Alumni Association bestowed on him its Community Service Award.
Patrick and Lily used their reparation funds to co-found the Okura Mental Health Leadership Foundation (OMHLF) to promote leadership, research and training in human services. OMHLF has impacted U.S. Congressional Policy regarding Asian American and Pacific Islander health issues. Okura also founded the National Asian Pacific American Families Against Substance Abuse (NAPAFASA) in 1988, as well as the Asian American Psychological Association (AAPA).
Lily A. Okura (1919-2005) was born in Santa Barbara, CA. In her younger years, she was recognized for her talent as a dancer and also appeared in several movies including Oil for the Lamps of China. She represented the city of Long Beach in the Tournament of Roses Parade in 1936 and participated in talent contests during Nisei Week. In 1939, she obtained her Bachelor's degree in Business Administration from Long Beach Business College and continued her studies at the University of Nebraska, Omaha.
Once the Okuras relocated to Nebraska, Lily worked with the YWCA in Omaha, where she started off as a secretary and eventually served as interim Executive Director. She moved on to become an administrator at the C. Meyer Louis Children's Therapy Center at the University of Nebraska College of Medicine and then later the Director of Volunteer Services. In 1972, hoping to rest, she moved to Bethesda, Maryland, but was recruited by the Director of Public Relations at the Corporation for Public Broadcasting and held the position of Director of Personnel until her retirement in 1982.
With her administrative experience, Lily managed the OMHLF and was also heavily involved in Altrusa International, a worldwide organization of professionals that aims to better the lives of others. She was recognized for her leadership, consistently serving on their Board of Directors and holding other positions. She took an active role with JACL at regional and national levels, and was the first woman elected to their National Board of Directors. She served in positions such as National Vice President of General Operations, Vice President, National Chair for the JACL's Japanese American of the Biennium Committee, and Editor of the Washington, D.C. chapter's D.C. News Notes. Overcome by grief with Patrick's passing in January 2005, Lily died less than five months later.
Source: "K. Patrick and Lily A. Okura Collection at UCLA." UCLA Asian American Studies Center. http://www.aasc.ucla.edu/okura/okura_about.aspx.
Scope and Contents
The Pat and Lily Okura papers range from 1912-2009 and contain files that document K. Patrick Okura's professional career, minority health advocacy, appointments, consultancies, community engagement, Lily A. Okura's life, involvement with the Japanese American Citizens League (JACL), World War II experience, personal records, correspondence, and resources.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: K. Patrick Okura professional career files, 1934-1999
Series 2: Minority health advocacy files, 1961-2005
Series 3: Appointments and consultancies files, 1972-2003
Series 4: Community engagement files, 1930-2005
Series 5: Lily A. Okura files, 1941-2004
Series 6: Japanese American Citizens League (JACL) files, 1934-2004
Series 7: World War II experience files, 1941-1990
Series 8: Personal record files, 1912-2009
Series 9: Correspondence files, 1932-2005
Series 10: Resource files, 1915-2004
Related Materials
Collection 2010
Japanese American Research Project (Yuji Ichioka) collection of material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Collection 2354
Kay Sugahara papers (Collection 2354). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Okura, Lily, 1919- -- Archives; Okura, Pat, 1911- -- Archives; Japanese Americans -- Civil rights
- Series 1: K. Patrick Okura professional career files, 1934-1999
  Scope and Contents
  Okura's professional career files document his work with the County of Los Angeles Civil Service Commission, County of Los Angeles Department of Charities, City of Los Angeles Civil Service Commission, Boys Town, Douglas County Juvenile Courts and Probation, Nebraska Psychiatric Institute, University of Nebraska (NPIUN), National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH), and Hahnemann University.
  - County of Los Angeles Civil Service Commission, 1934-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - County of Los Angeles Dept. of Charities, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    This contains a survey of tuberculosis cases.
  - City of Los Angeles Civil Service Commission, 1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - City of Los Angeles Civil Service Commission, 1942-1947 (Box 183, Folder 1-2)
    This contains employment termination and personnel action records.
  - City of Los Angeles Civil Service Commission, 1939 October (Box 186, Folder 1)
    This contains materials on the 31st meeting of Civil Service Assembly of United States and Canada, held at Fairmont Hotel in San Francisco, CA. This also includes a list of registrants and photographs.
  - Boys Town, 1942-1997 (Box 1, Folder 4-12)
    Folder 4 contains photographs of Okura with Father Flanagan in 1943.
  - Boys Town, 1953-1994 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    Folder 2 contains a Boys Town High School Pylon yearbook from 1958.
  - Boys Town, 1943-1958 (Box 186, Folder 2-3)
    Folder 2 contains a Boy Scouts of America certificate of completion of Scout leaders training presented to K. Patrick Okura. Folder 3 contains class photographs from 1945-58.
  - Douglas County Juvenile Courts and Probation, Omaha, Nebraska, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Nebraska Psychiatric Institute, University of Nebraska (NPIUN), 1962-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9-12)
  - NPIUN, 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
    This contains files on the Joint Commission on Mental Health and Children, and White House Conference on Children.
  - NPIUN, 1964 (Box 186, Folder 4)
    This contains a certificate of appreciation presented by the Japanese American Citizens League (JACL).
  - NPIUN, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    This contains files on the White House Conference on Children.
  - National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH), 1971-1980 (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
  - NIMH general records, 1971-1981 (Box 5, Folder 1-10)
    This contains work files of Bertram Brown activities. Folder 7 contains White House briefing from 1972 and reception for AA Leaders.
  - NIMH general records, 1973-1980 (Box 6, Folder 1-12)
    Folder 1 contains materials on a 1973 visit by Ann Landers.
  - NIMH general records, 1976-1983 (Box 7, Folder 1-11)
  - NIMH - International mental health, 1967-1975 (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
    This contains collaborative research exchange with Japan.
  - NIMH - International mental health, 1973-1981 (Box 9, Folder 1-13)
  - NIMH - International mental health, 1975-1981 (Box 10, Folder 1-9)
  - NIMH - International mental health, 1973-1979 (Box 222, Folder 1)
    This contains a photograph album of various research exchange meetings with Japan.
  - NIMH - International mental health, 1972-1978 (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
    This contains collaborative research exchange with Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR).
  - NIMH - International mental health, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    This contains collaborative research exchange with Thailand.
  - NIMH - International mental health, 1979-1981 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    This contains collaborative research exchange with People's Republic of China.
  - NIMH - International mental health, 1978-1981 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
    This contains materials on Sino-American Conference on Social Welfare Development, held in Taipei, Taiwan.
  - NIMH - International mental health, 1980-1981 (Box 186, Folder 5)
    This contains a closing speech and oversize photograph of Sino-American Conference, Taipei, Taiwan.
  - NIMH - Indochinese refugees services, 1977-1980 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
  - NIMH - Indochinese refugees services, 1979-1981 (Box 12, Folder 1-8)
  - NIMH - Indochinese refugees services, 1980-1983 (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
    Folders 3-4 contains Refugee Reports newsletter.
  - NIMH - Asian American Mental Health Conference (AAMHC), San Francisco, 1971-1975 (Box 13, Folder 5-7)
    This contains conference planning with minority psychologists, social and human service providers, and various organizations.
  - NIMH - AAMHC, San Francisco, 1972 April 27-29 (Box 185, Folder 1-11)
    This contains enlarged conference photographic panels. Folder 1 contains 35mm black and white slides.
  - NIMH - Demonstration Project for Asian Americans (AA), 1973-1980 (Box 13, Folder 8-11)
    This contains a folder of AA Mental Health Federation. Also contains final reports on Asian wives of U.S. servicemen; AA service needs of Chicago community; and the Korean American child at school and at home, by Bok-Lim Kim and Margaret Condon
  - NIMH - Alcohol, Drug Abuse, and Mental Health Administration (ADAMHA), 1971-1986 (Box 14, Folder 1-10)
    Folder 10 contains a photograph of First NIMH Women's Council, 1972 and Task Force on AA Women Report by Washington State, 1976.
  - NIMH - ADAMHA, 1978-1980 (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
    Folder 1-2 contains lobbying efforts of Asian Pacific American (APA) Advisory Committee to establish White House liaison officer. Folder 3 contains a newsletter.
  - NIMH - Center for Minority Group Mental Health Programs, 1972-1985 (Box 15, Folder 4-12)
    Folder 12 contains a Handbook of AA&PI Mental Health by James Morishima, Stanley Sue, et al., 1979.
  - NIMH - President's Commission on Mental Health, 1977-1978 (Box 16, Folder 1-9)
    Folder 9 contains a report submitted to the Commission by the special populations subpanel on Asian American and Pacific Islander (AA&PI) and group photograph with Rosalynn Carter.
  - NIMH - President's Commission on Mental Health, 1979-1980 (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
    This contains materials on conferences on ethnic minority mental health curriculum development.
  - NIMH - American Orthopsychiatric Association, 1977-1999 (Box 17, Folder 3-7)
  - NIMH - American Psychiatric Association, 1973-1977 (Box 18, Folder 1-6)
    Folder 1 contains photographs of the 126th annual meeting in Honolulu, HI.
  - NIMH - American Public Health Association, 1976-1980 (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
  - NIMH - U.S. Committee for International Council on Social Welfare, 1976-1980 (Box 19, Folder 4-6)
  - NIMH - World Congress of Psychiatry, 1975-1977 (Box 19, Folder 7-8)
  - NIMH - World Congress of Psychiatry, 1977 (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
    Folder 6 contains a photograph of Rosalynn Carter at the World Congress on Mental Health in 1977.
  - NIMH - World Federation for Mental Health, 1975-1977 (Box 20, Folder 3-7)
  - NIMH - World Federation for Mental Health, 1978-1981 (Box 21, Folder 1-3)
  - Hahnemann University general records, 1983-1988, undated (Box 21, Folder 4-8)
  - Hahnemann University general records, 1980-1986 (Box 22, Folder 1-12)
  - Hahnemann University general records, 1981-1986 (Box 23, Folder 1-17)
  - Hahnemann University general records, 1979-1986 (Box 24, Folder 1-3)
  - Hahnemann University - International mental health, 1982-1986 (Box 24, Folder 4-9)
    This contains a collaboration with Japan Association of Psychiatric Hospitals.
  - Hahnemann University - International mental health, 1983-1984 (Box 216, Folder 1)
    This contains a photograph album of a visit to Japan Association of Psychiatric Hospitals.
  - Hahnemann University - International mental health, 1984-1990 (Box 25, Folder 1-3)
  - Hahnemann University - International mental health, 1983-1986 (Box 25, Folder 4-9)
    This contains a collaboration with Japan, Korea, China, and Thailand.
  - Hahnemann University - International mental health, 1983 (Box 217, Folder 1)
    This contains a photograph album of Sino-American Life Change and Stress educational study tour.
  - Hahnemann University - International mental health, 1986-1987 (Box 218, Folder 1)
    This contains a photograph album of collaboration visits to Japan.
  - Hahnemann University - International mental health, 1985-1986 (Box 26, Folder 1-2)
    This contains a collaboration with Korea and Thailand.
  - Hahnemann University - Immigrant refugee concerns, 1980-1986 (Box 26, Folder 3-7)
    This contains materials on the Southeast Asian Mutual Assistance Associations Coalition.
  - Hahnemann University - Immigrant refugee concerns, 1981-1988 (Box 27, Folder 1-2)
  - Hahnemann University - Asian American (AA) mental health, 1985-1986 (Box 27, Folder 3-7)
  - Hahnemann University - AA mental health, 1981-1990 (Box 28, Folder 1-7)
  - Hahnemann University - AA mental health, 1981-1992 (Box 29, Folder 1-4)
  - Hahnemann University - Bertram S. Brown, 1970-1973 (Box 29, Folder 5-8)
    This contains papers and speeches.
  - Hahnemann University - Bertram S. Brown, 1974-1979 (Box 30, Folder 1-6)
  - Hahnemann University - Bertram S. Brown, 1976-1985 (Box 31, Folder 1-4)
    This contains papers, speeches, and curriculum vitae.
- Series 2: Minority health advocacy files, 1961-2005
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audio and audiovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
  The Minority health advocacy files document community-based work with Asian American Social Workers (AASW), Pacific/Asian Coalition (PAC), Pacific/Asian Elderly Research Project (PAERP), National PA Resource Center on Aging (NPARCA), National APA Families Against Substance Abuse (NAPAFASA), Okura Mental Health Leadership Foundation (OMHLF), Asian American Psychological Association (AAPA), and other Asian American/Pacific Islander (AAPI) community advocacy organizations.
  - Asian American Social Workers (AASW) - Asian American (AA) Community Mental Health Training Center, 1973-1980 (Box 31, Folder 5-6)
  - AASW - Asian American Mental Health Conference (AAMHC), 1971-1972 (Box 31, Folder 7-8)
    This contains a conference program and planning committee notes.
  - AASW - AAMHC, 1971-1973 (Box 32, Folder 1-5)
    This contains a conference program and post-conference evaluation. Folder 4 contains photographs.
  - AASW - AA Mental Health Federation, 1973-1974 (Box 32, Folder 6-7)
  - Pacific/Asian Coalition (PAC) general records, 1974-1978 (Box 32, Folder 8-11)
    This contains newsletters.
  - PAC general records, 1976-1979 (Box 33, Folder 1-8)
    This contains board records, grant applications and proposals. Folder 1 contains materials from the 1976 national conference held in San Francisco.
  - PAC general records, 1973-1981 (Box 34, Folder 1-3)
    This contains correspondence and Ford Kuramoto memos.
  - PAC - Pacific American (PA) Mental Health Research Project, 1979-1982 (Box 34, Folder 4-7)
    Folders 5-7 contain project reports submitted to the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH).
  - Pacific/Asian Elderly Research Project (PAERP), 1977-1978 (Box 34, Folder 8-11)
    This contains correspondence, reports, proposals, and conferences.
  - PAERP, 1977-1978 (Box 35, Folder 1-10)
    This contains proposals, conferences, newsletters, and Understanding the Pacific/Asian Elderly report series.
  - National Pacific American Resource Center on Aging (NPARCA), 1981-1983 (Box 35, Folder 11-12)
    This contains Pacific/Asians: The Wisdom of Age proceedings, a White House Conference on Aging mini-conference held in San Francisco, CA in January 1981.
  - NPARCA, 1981-1998 (Box 36, Folder 1-5)
    Folders 1-2 contain newsletters. Folders 3-5 contain files on various PA elderly programs across the nation.
  - National Asian Pacific American Families Against Substance Abuse (NAPAFASA), 1987-1988 (Box 36, Folder 6-10)
    This contains proposals, work files, and conference files. Folder 8 contains files for the White House Conference for a Drug Free America. Folder 9-10 contains files on the National AA Conference on Substance Abuse Prevention.
  - NAPAFASA, 1986-1995 (Box 37, Folder 1-10)
    This contains conference and program files, including Pacific Asian Alcohol Program, and regional What Works conference in San Francisco, CA.
  - NAPAFASA, 1991-1999 (Box 38, Folder 1-5)
    This contains conference and program files, and reports.
  - Okura Mental Health Leadership Foundation (OMHLF) general records, 1988-2003 (Box 38, Folder 6-10)
    This contains organizational and Annual Week in Washington Leadership Training Program files. Also contains lists of fellows and scholarship recipients.
  - OMHLF - organizational events, 1993-1999 (Box 38, Folder 11-13)
    This contains files on special events, including White House visit with Vice President Al Gore, and the 10-year anniversary of OMHLF.
  - OMHLF - organizational events, 1988 (Box 223, Folder 1)
    This contains a photograph album of OMHLF launch and K. Patrick Okura's 77th birthday celebration.
  - OMHLF - organizational events, 2002 (Box 221, Folder 2)
    This contains a photograph album of the 10th Annual Week in Washington leadership seminar.
  - OMHLF - K. Patrick Okura oral history interviews, 1991-1993 (Box 159, Folder 5-10)
    This contains unedited transcripts and notes of scholarship recipient Diane Fujino. Folder 5 contains autobiographical notes and travel summaries.
  - OMHLF - K. Patrick Okura oral history interviews, 1991-1993 (Box 160, Folder 1)
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Audio materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
    This contains a six audiocassettes of interviews conducted and taped by Diane Fujino.
  - Community Mental Health - Office of Minority Health, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 1991-2000 (Box 39, Folder 1-5)
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
    This contains newsletters and conference files. Folder 3 contains a VHS recording of National Teleconference.
  - Community Mental Health - AA Psychiatrists, 1975-1982 (Box 39, Folder 6-8)
    This contains materials affiliated with the American Psychiatric Association.
  - Community Mental Health - AA Psychiatrists, 1973-1976 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Community Mental Health - Asian American Psychological Association (AAPA), 1974-1995 (Box 40, Folder 2-7)
    Folder 4 contains materials on the 2nd biennial convention and a photograph of K. Patrick Okura with a Community Service Award.
  - Community Mental Health - AAPA, 1976-2004 (Box 41, Folder 1-12)
    This contains conference and general files. File 11 contains a reproduction of the Lifetime Achievement Award presented to K. Patrick Okura in 2000.
  - Community Mental Health - AAPA, 1975-2005 (Box 42, Folder 1-7)